<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A godly wil and confession of the Christian faythe, made by Rychard Brasier, late auditour to the kinges maiestie in Ireland, whiche be dydde most constantly cleaue vnto during the time that he lyued, worthy to be read by all Christians</title>
            <author>Brasier, Richard.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1551</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A68976</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3552.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113319</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848555</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848555</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13656</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A68976)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13656)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 642:04a)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A godly wil and confession of the Christian faythe, made by Rychard Brasier, late auditour to the kinges maiestie in Ireland, whiche be dydde most constantly cleaue vnto during the time that he lyued, worthy to be read by all Christians</title>
                  <author>Brasier, Richard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Ihon Day: dwelling ouer Aldersgate beneth S. Martins],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1551?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; publication date suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A godly wyl made by Rychard Brasier.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 3552a in reel guide.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Creeds --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13656:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13656:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>decorative border</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>¶ A godly wil and confeſſion of the Chriſtian faythe, made by Rychard Braſier, late Auditour to the kin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges maieſti in Ire<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>land, whiche he dydde moſt conſtantly cleaue vnto during the time that he lyued, worthy to be read of all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:13656:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13656:2"/>
            <head>¶ To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere haſt thou (gentle reder) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true copy of the laſt wil and teſtament of Richard Braſier, late Auditour for the kyngs maieſty in Ireland, wherin is briefly, but yet clearely declared the fayth in Chriſt, which the ſaid Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard did profeſſe in hys life time, &amp; conſtantly cleaue vnto in the tyme of hys departyng oute of this lyfe. Whych hys laſt wil and confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Chriſtian faith, the ſayd Rychard wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to be openly declared in a Sermon made at his funeral in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church of S. Patrike in Diue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyn, wher he lyeth buryed, to the entent that the mouthes of ſuch ſlaunderers as do commonly imagine the reca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tacion of faythful Chriſtians at the time of their departing out of this world, myght be ſtopped. And becauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> report of this confeſſion of fayth is not yet beleued of manye ſuperſtitious me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> would al Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld in their laſt houre recant their aſſured hope of ſaluation through Chriſt only without any our deſeruinges: it hath bene thought good to ſuch as the ſaid Richard put in truſt to ſe his wil ful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>filled, to cauſe this (the very true copy hereof) to be imprinted, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might ſe &amp; iudge. Beſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ching the to read &amp; reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber what Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faith Richard Braſiar ſtode vnto in the end, &amp; what euery true me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of Chriſt muſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe &amp; ſtand vnto. The merciful goodnes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord preſerue the to the ende, that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> maieſt be ſalfe. So be it.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:13656:3"/>
            <opener>In the name of God. Amen</opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Richard Bra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyer the Kynges maieſties Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, of his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cees Realme of Ireland, beynge of a hole and per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fect memorye, do make my teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment &amp; laſt wyll, the fyfth day of Iune, the .iiii. yere of the raygne of our ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerayne Lord kyng Edwarde the ſyxte, by the grace of God king of England, Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and Ireland, defendour of the fayth and of the church of England and alſo of Irela<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de in earth the ſupreme head, in maner &amp; forme as hereafter followeth.</p>
            <p>Fyrſt and before al other thynges, I com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myt me vnto God the eternall Father, and to hys excedyng great mercy, truſting with out any dour or miſtruſt, that by the merites of hys moſt deare and beſt beloued ſon, that moſt innocent and immaculate lambe, that pure and vndefyled lambe, whych taketh a way the ſynnes of the world, our only ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, Redemer, Mediatour, &amp; Iuſtyfyer, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte, for whoſe ſake God the father is pacifyed, ſatiſfyed and ſette at one wyth man, and by vertue of hys moſt bytter, but
<pb facs="tcp:13656:3"/> yet hys moſt precious deathe and paſſyon, and hys gloryous reſurreccion, I haue and ſhal haue free remiſſion and forgyuenes of my ſynnes, and that in the laſt daye I ſhall ryſe agayne both body and ſoule according as it is wrytten in Iob the .xix. c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>p. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue that mi redemer liueth, and that in the laſt day I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>al ryſe out of the earthe, and in my fleſh ſhal ſe my Sauiour Ieſus Chriſte. And I bele<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e that I ſhal ſe the almyghtye goodnes and maieſty of God, in the land of the lyuyng, and that I ſhall be a Citizen in the Celeſtiall and heauenlye Ieruſalem, in the company of many thouſandes of Aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, in ioy inexplycable, and thys my hope is laid vp in the boſome of my hart by faith. Althoughe I confeſſe and knowledge that I haue bene and am a miſerable and wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched ſynner, whych haue not kepte anye of the commaundementes of God, but haue reſyſted hys wyl many wayes. An euyl tree am I that haue broughte foorthe no good fruit, for by nature I am the child of wrath in all that maye be named, be it ſecrete or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, dooe I knowledge my ſelfe gyltye, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng hereof repentaunce and am ſorye for it, euen from the very bottome of my harte, beſechyng the almyghty Lord God heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father, that it wyl pleaſe hym not to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer me to ſtycke in the depth of my ſynnes, neither impute the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto me, but graciouſly
<pb facs="tcp:13656:4"/> to delyuer me from theym throughe Ieſus Chriſt hys ſonne and our Lord. Alſo, foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as it hath pleaſed God of hys vnme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurable bounty and infinite great mercy, to cal me vnto the knowledge of the veritye &amp; truth of hys moſt holy word and goſpel, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of the bothomleſſe pyt of hell, wherinto I had caſt my ſelfe by my own iniquity, and ſynce that tyme that I haue knowen that infallyble truth and verity, I haue vtterlye refuſed and forſaken the moſte deteſtable &amp; abhominable vyces of idolatry, as offeryng to idols and goyng of pilgrimages and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of peſtiferous popyſh maſſes, ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion and ipocriſy, wyth all the tradicions &amp; execrable cerymonyes inuented by byſhops of Rome &amp; theyr wycked adherentes, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>with both I and all the hole world beſydes hath bene blynded and ſeduced, and yet for the more part are, I praye God amende the ſame at hys good pleaſure, and haue who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly geuen ouer my ſelfe to the ſayd truthe of Gods moſt holye woorde, and haue mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned the ſame to the beſt of my power, al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>though the ſame was but very ſmal, euen ſo do I now truſt by the abundaunte grace of God, to end my lyfe in the ſame. And to the intent that after my departure oute of thys lyfe, the wycked worldlynges and papiſtes whych hath a world of wyckednes in theyr tonges, ſhal not detracte, backbite &amp; ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb facs="tcp:13656:4"/> me, ſaying: that I haue forſaken thoſe opinions, fayth, truſt and belie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, in the mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyes and promyſes of God, throughe hys word, neyther touchynge my belefe nor my opinion of the two reuerend and holy miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, ſacramentes, ſygnes, tokens or ſealed obligacions and commemoracions, whych I haue mayntayned now in my lyfe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to Gods word, that is to ſay of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme and of the holy Supper of the worde, I wyll bryefely declare my opynyon in the ſame, hereafter followyng.</p>
            <p>Fyrſt as touchyng my fayth and belefe. I beleue in God the Father almyghty, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of heauen &amp; earth. And in Ieſus Chriſte hys only ſonne our Lord, whyche was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued by the holy Ghoſt, and borne of the vyrgyn Mary. Suffered vnder Ponce Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, crucifyed, dead, and buryed, deſcended into hel, and roſe agayne the thyrd day fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dead, aſcended vnto heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ſytteth on the ryghte hande of God the Father al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myghty, and from thence ſhal come againe to iudge the quycke and the deade. I beleue in the holy Goſt, and that ther is an holy v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyuerſal Catholyke church, whyche is the congregacion and felowſhyp of ſayntes, re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſſion and forgyuenes of ſyns. The reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reccion of the fleſh, and euerlaſtyng lyfe.</p>
            <p>At the fyrſt I beleue in one God &amp; father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, the whyche is the
<pb facs="tcp:13656:5"/> Lorde of heauen and earthe, and Creatoure of all creatures, yea, he is father of vs all, whych hath elected vs to be hys childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Ieſu Chriſt, and therfore ſhall we hym alonly worſhyp, and beſide him none other gods. Alſo we ſhal feare hym as an almygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tye God, and as a mercyful father we ſhall loue hym wyth all our hartes, wyth all our ſoule, wyth al our power, and wyth all our ſtrengthe and mynde, and vpon hym muſte ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d al our hope, for he is the father of light, of whom al mankynd lyueth, and hath euer laſting ſaluacion, and al other perfect gifts pertaynyng eyther to the body or to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoul, haue we from hym through Ieſus Chriſte, hys ſonne and our Lord. Furthermore, I be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leue in Ieſus Chriſt the ſonne of the liuyng God, whych is the very bryghtnes of his fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers glory, and the very Image of his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce, yea, he is the only begotten ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of the father, come forth out of the mouthe of the moſt hyeſt God, fyrſt born before al crea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures. Through whom al thynges are crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we haue redempcion, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly remiſſion of ſynnes, through hys bloude, wyth the which he hath waſhed and clenſed vs al from ſynne, and hath alſo reconcyled vs agayne to hys moſte holye and gloryous father, that wer afore enemies to God. For after the tyme that God had made man af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hys owne image and ſimilitude, he ſette
<pb facs="tcp:13656:5"/> hym into Paradyſe, that he ſhoulde eate of al the frutes of the garden of pleaſure, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptyng hym only the tree of knowledge of good and euyl, but man diſobeyed the Lord hys God, and tranſgreſſed hys commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement Through the whych diſobedyence, and tranſgreſſion of the godly commaunde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, death &amp; curſſe came ouer al ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kynde. And when ther was no helpe nor comforte for man, wherby he myght haue bene rede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med or delyuered out of ſathans power, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had God the mercyful father pyty on man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, and promiſed them a ſede, namely Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſu Chriſt hys only begotten ſon, the whych ſhould tread vpon the head of the Serpent, and ouer come the diuel, and reſtore them to lyfe agayne. And lykewyſe as God is righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous in all hys wayes and holye in all hys workes, and true in al hys wordes, ſo hathe he kepte al hys promiſes trulye. And as the tyme of hys promyſe was fulfylled, god let hys word deſcend into the wombe of the vir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gin Mary, and by the workyng of the holye Goſt became fleſh, as Ihon in his fyrſt chap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter of hys Goſpel wytneſſeth ſayinge: The word became fleſh, and dwelt amongeſt vs, and we ſaw hys glorye, as the glorye of the onelye begotten ſonne of the father, full of grace and veritye. Alſo thys onlye begotten ſon of God by the power of the holy Goſte became man, &amp; is become lyke vnto vs in all
<pb facs="tcp:13656:6"/> thynges, (ſynne only except) he hath ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red death for our ſakes, and hathe taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way Sathans power, and reſtored lyfe in a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gayne, yea, he is made vnto vs wiſdom and ryghtuouſnes, ſatiſfaccion and redempcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And lykewyſe as he dyed for our ſyns, and went downe into hel, ſo is he ryſen agayne the thyrd day fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death through the power of hys father, for our ryghtuouſnes, iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacion and ſaluacion. And as he ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tymes ſhewed hym ſelfe after hys reſurreccion vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hys diſciples, ſo aſcended he vnto heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in theyr preſence, and ſytteth at the ryghte hand of the almyghty Father, aboue al rule myght, and dominion, &amp; aboue all that may be named, not only in this world, but alſo in the world to come, &amp; hath ſubdued al thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges vnder hys fete, In ſumma he is a Lord aboue al Lords, and a king aboue al kings, yea, he is an almyghtye God wyth hys fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And neuertheleſſe he is alſo our onli ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uocate and mediatour, our only hye prieſte, the ſacrifice that he hathe done once for all for our ſins, abideth of valure for euermore.</p>
            <p>Furthermore lykewyſe as Chriſte oure Lord is aſcended vp into heauen, and there ſytteth vpon the ryght hand of God his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, euen ſo ſhal he come againe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen wyth the dominion of hys father, and with thouſandes of Aungels for to geue euerye man reward after hys workes, yea, euen to
<pb facs="tcp:13656:6"/> iudge the quycke and the dead. I beleue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in the holy Goſt, God wyth the father &amp; the ſonne, whych holye Goſt is a teacher of all Chriſten people, and he doth cloth &amp; gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhe them wyth hys giftes, and geueth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one the meaſure of faith after his own holy wil, and keepeth them vnmoueable in one faithe, for he is a ruler of the Chriſtian congregacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. He is alſo the anointme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wher with all the Chriſtian are anoynted, and of that behalfe are called the anoynted of the Lorde. So is this holye Ghoſte geuen vnto the Chriſtiane as an earneſt of theyr inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, to the redempcion, and they agayne be hys owne to the prayſe of his glory, to be briefe, it is vnpoſſible wythoute thys holye holy Goſt to know God ryghtly, or wyth al the hole harte to beleue vpon hym, or to call vpon him as a father, and therfore doth god poure thys hys holy ſpirit vpon hys childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wherby they may ryghtly knowe hym, and ryghtly beleue in hym, and as a ryghte fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther call vpon him. This is my beliefe to the father, the ſonne: and the holy Goſt, whych thre perſons I knoledge to be God, whoſe ſeate is heauen, and the earth is a bench for hys feete, yea the whych is an euerlaſtynge an almyghty, a ryghtuous and a moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyful God, the whych alone wyl be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ped and ſerued, for he alone can healpe vs, whych he doth for hys names ſake, and not
<pb facs="tcp:13656:7"/> for our rightuouſnes ſake.</p>
            <p>Furthermore as I haue ſaid, that al they that do beleue, ar ioyned together &amp; through the holy goſt knit in vnity, ſo is ther a Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtian church the whych is buylded of lyuing ſtones, whych church is the houſe of God, and the houſe of God is the congregacion of God, and the congregacion of God, is the body of Chriſt, and ſeyng that al right chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians are one bodye in the whyche they all through one ſpirit are baptiſed, ſo muſt ther be a communion of Sayntes, namely that all ſayntes or true beleuers, are alſo ioyned together in vnity as the members of one bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. And in thys communion of Sayntes is remiſſyon of ſyns, and that wythoute it, is no ſynne forgiuen, nor any hope of ſaluaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Yea, lyke as it is vnpoſſible that a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber can lyue that is not in the bodye, ſo is it vnpoſſible that any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may lyue in hys ſoul and can be releaſed out of death by remyſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſynne, the whyche is not a member of the body of Chriſt, for Chriſt hath reconcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vs al vnto God hys father in one bodye, and therfore muſt al they ſtande in varience that are no members of thys bodye, of the which Chriſt is the head to the which he gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth ſaluacion. Ther ſhal be alſo a generall reſurreccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the fleſh, namely that all they that are dead ſhal ryſe a gayne, ſome to euer laſtyng lyfe, and ſome to euerlaſting damp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacion,
<pb facs="tcp:13656:7"/> and they that ſhal liue and remaine vpon the earth, vntyl the commyng of oure Lord Ieſu Chriſt, they ſhall be chaunged in the twynklyng of an eye at the tyme of the laſt trumpet. The trumpet ſaith Paule ſhal blow, and the dead ſhall ryſe vncorruptible, and we ſhal be chaunged, for thys corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyble body muſte put on vncorrupcion, and thys mortal body muſt put on immortality. At the laſt, is ther alſo an euerlaſtynge lyfe, whyche al they ſhall receyue that beleue on Ieſus Chriſt and ſtedfaſtlye abyde in good workes, ſekyng prayſe, honour, and immor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tality in the lyfe to come. Thys is the ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me of my fayth and belefe, through the whyche fayth al the ryghtuous lyue, and wythoute the which beliefe, no man may pleaſe God. Therefore the euerlaſtynge God be bleſſed that oute of hys vnmeaſurable mercye and grace hath giuen me thys faythe throughe Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
            <p>Now foloweth my fayth and opinion of the ſacramental token of baptiſme.</p>
            <p>Baptyſme is a ſacramentall token, the whyche is gyuen vs of Chriſte, and is at the fyrſt an entryng into the Chriſtian congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacion, as Paule ſayeth: we are baptiſed in one ſpirite, to be one body i. Cor. xii.</p>
            <p>Secondarely, Baptyſme is a fountayne of regeneracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as Paul witneſſeth. Tit. iii. ſaying that Chriſt hath ſaued vs bi the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine
<pb facs="tcp:13656:8"/> of the newe byrthe and renuing of the holy ghoſt, not that the water doth ſaue vs, for nothyng can ſaue vs but only God. Eſa xliii. but ſeynge that our Lord Ieſu Chriſt, hath ſpoken, that he that beleueth &amp; is bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſed ſhall be ſaued. Marc. xvi. And goddes word is verity and truth. Ihon. xvii. And his promyſes may not fayle, Pſal. cxlvii. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt baptyme nedes brynge ſaluation, vnto them that in beleue are baptyſed, not for the workes ſake, but for gods word and promyſes Deu. viii.</p>
            <p>Thirdly baptime is a couenant of a good conſcyence to God, firſt of Pete. iii. namely that he that in beleue is baptyſed byndeth hym ſelf, or maketh a couenaunt with god, that from thenceforth he wil liue after his wil. And on this couenauntes behalfe, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che muſte be done oute of a cleane faythfull heart, hath the baptyme power, and not for the water ſake, wherewith the filthineſſe of the fleſh is waſhed away, but withoute it be that the hearts of them that are baptiſed be cleanſed. Actes. xv. Through goddes word. Ihon. xv. The water can not cleanſe them, wherwyth it is alſo proued that baptyſme wythoute faythe maye in no wyſe bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed. Foorthelye baptyſme ſygnyfyeth an offerynge of the fleſhe, and a reſurrecci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into a newe lyfe, as we haue to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maynes. vi. Knowe ye not ſaythe Saynte Paule, that all we whyche are baptyſed in
<pb facs="tcp:13656:8"/> the name of Ieſu Chriſt, are baptyſed to die wyth hym, therfore are we buried wyth him by baptyſme for to dye, that lykewyſe as Chriſt was raiſed vp fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death to lyfe, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glory of the father, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo we ſhuld walke in a newe lyfe. Thys is nowe ſhortly expreſſed what baptiſme is and what it ſignifyeth. But for aſmuch as all the former ſcriptures are ſpoken of them onlye that be of yeres of diſcreſſion before they receiue the faythe of Chriſt, it is not altering of the inſtitucion &amp; word of Chriſt, to baptiſe the innocents &amp; in fa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes. For as in circumciſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the old law, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faith of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> parents ſufficed to make the child one of the choſen people of God, not wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, that the circumciſion of the fleſh, is not circumciſion, as Paul writeth to the Ro. ii. but the circumciſion of the hert, euen ſo the baptiſme of our infants not withſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dinge that the waſhynge of the bodye in wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter is not baptyſme, but the waſhynge of the ſoule in the bloude of Chriſte by faythe, yet ſhall the faythe of the parentes be accep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted of God. And theyr chyldren made mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the churche of Chriſt thereby. And al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo I beleue that god dothe moue the heartes of the infantes that be hys wyth the holye ghoſt, If any require witneſſes of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, for thys aſſercyon that chyldrene or infantes be made members of the church of Chriſte by the faythe of theyre parentes, Lette hym reade and conſyder well the
<pb facs="tcp:13656:9"/> ſtory of Sampſon and Samuel, wyth other lyke ſtoryes of the old teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, wherin may eaſely be perceyued how God dyd then ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the children for the parents fayth. Let hym conſyder alſo the ſtoryes of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, wherin appeareth how Chriſt wold not haue the children kept from hym, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr parentes brought the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to hym that he might lay hys hand vpon them, and how certayne chyldren were cured and healed of diſeaſes euen for the fayth that was found in theyr parentes. And laſt of al, it is euydent both in the Actes of the Apoſtles, and in the Epy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles of certaine of them, that when certaine men receiued the Goſpell, both they &amp; theyr whole houſhold were baptyſed. Where it is not to be thought that the infantes wer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected becauſe they could not vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the Apoſtles preachyng. For S. Paule writing to the Corinthians, ſayd .i. Corin. vii. As co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernyng the chyldren begotten betwene an Heathen man, and a faithful woman, or be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>twene a Heatheniſh woman, and a faithful man, the children are cleane, by reaſon that one of his parentes is faithful And what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing ſhuld he meane thereby, but that God accepteth thoſe children for members of his church, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the faithfull parentes do willingly bring to the fountain of regenera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion therto receiue the ſigne of the euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting couenant betwene God and vs. Thys
<pb facs="tcp:13656:9"/> is with the ſhorteſt my faythe and opinion of baptyſme.</p>
            <p>Nowe foloweth lykewyſe my fayth and opinion of the ſupper of the Lord,</p>
            <p>The ſupper of the Lorde is a memoryall token of the ſufferinge and deathe of Ieſu Chriſt &amp; is inſtituted of Chriſt for this cauſe that the faythfull congregacyon of Ieſu Chriſt ſhulde come together, for to ſhew the deathe of Ieſu Chriſte and hys benefytes, lauddynge and thankynge hym, magnyfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge hys holye name, and then alſo eate of thys breade, and dryncke of thys wyne, to a remembraunce that Chriſt hathe geuen hys body and ſhed his bloud for vs. Math. xxvi. And becauſe that it is a comen vſe, that a to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken of remembraunce, hath the name of the thinge that is remembred by it. Therefore hath Chriſt called the breade his bodye and the wyne hys bloud: not that hys ſubſtance is in the breade and wyne, but that we ſhuld remember him therby. Likewiſe as the Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter lambe was called the paſſynge by, and yet was it not in it ſelf the very paſſyng by, ſeinge nowe that the Eaſter lambe hath the name of the thynge that the Iſraelytes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred by it, and wherby they might euer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>laſtinglye keepe in remembraunce the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites of God, right conuenient is it y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt hath called the bread his body and the wine his bloude, becauſe that we ſhuld remember
<pb facs="tcp:13656:10"/> therby his death and paſſion, yea the only ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crifice of his body which he hath ſuffered to be broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and his bloud to be ſhed for vs. Ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uertheles how be it that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> materiall body of Chriſt is not in the breade, nor his bloude in the wine, yet neuertheles is the ſupper of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord a partaking (but ſpiritually) of the bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dye and bloude of Chriſte as Paule ſaieth. Is not the cuppe of thankeſgeuing wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with we geue thankes a partakynge of the bloude of Chriſt? And the bread y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we breake is it not the partaking of the bodi of Chriſt? Theſe wordes of Paule do witnes clearely that the faithful eate the body of Chriſt ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritually vnder the breade and wine. Yea like<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wiſe as a Bryde receiueth her huſband with a ringe, euen ſo receiue the faithful Chriſt to be theyr owne and euerlaſtinge ſaluacion, but that ſome men wil haue that the bodely preſence ſhoulde be in the breade, is a greate miſſe vnderſtandinge of the godlye woorde, yea it is an Antichriſtes doctryne, whych is contrary both to our faith &amp; to al hole ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, for I beleue and holy ſcripture beareth witnes, that Chriſt after his reſurreccion is aſcended vp into heauen, and ſitteth vppon the right hand of his almighty father Rom. viii. And bydeth there as concerninge his bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dely preſence, but ſpiritually he hath promy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed to abide with vs to the end of the worlde in his woorde. Math. xxviii. And ſeinge that
<pb facs="tcp:13656:10"/> nowe Chriſte as concerning hys bodely pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſence abideth at the righthand of God hys father. Heb. x. ſo may not the body of Chriſt be in the breade. And againe it is againſte al truth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt at one time hath bene in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny or diuerſe places, as touchinge his body. Furthermore we do daily ſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dredeful ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry is ſprong out of the carnal vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge of theſe wordes of Chriſt. This is my body, &amp; yet daily ſpringeth: to the great &amp; ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hominable ſlaunder of the honor of god, ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> worſhip a piece of bread for their god, yea &amp; hold that to be their maker. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> papiſts locke him in gold and ſiluer, not reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bring what Paule &amp; Stephen witnes ſaying: The moſt higheſt wil not dwell in temples made with mans hands. Act. vii. and .xvii: O blind me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are ſo be witched of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whore that ye can not nor wil not beleue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> manifeſt truth. O blindnes and great preſumptuouſnes of the papiſtes, that wil take vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to teach Ieſu Chriſte oute of heauen into a piece of bread, which is conſumable, as we clearly ſe by experience, &amp; that it ſhulde be worſhipped for God, which is euerlaſting and vnchange<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>able. Now what remedy for I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not help it, therfore muſt I do as the Lord Ieſu Chriſt ſpake vnto his Apoſtels of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Phariſeis ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: Let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> go for thei are blind, &amp; leaders of the blynde, when one blind leadeth an other ſo fal they both into the ditche, Mat. xv. but
<pb facs="tcp:13656:11"/> the lord muſt be thanked, that out of his vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meaſurable grace hath opened our eies, that we can ſe and know, wherfore we ſhal take the bread and the wine in the ſupper, name<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly for a memorial and token of the ſuffering and death of Ieſu Chriſt, yea for the body &amp; bloud of Chriſte, but that for the hye names ſake, &amp; not of the material thinges behalfe, as is aboue rehearſed of the Eaſter Lambe.</p>
            <p>Furthermore the ſupper of the Lord is al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo a ioining togither of the Chriſten congre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in loue. And alſo the congregacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that wil hold this ſupper muſt be wel apointed &amp; ioined together in brotherlye loue, yea they muſt ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in one ſpirit &amp; ſoul. Ph. i. Hauing a burning loue, for Paule ſaithe: we many are one bred, &amp; one body, in aſmuch as we ar par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>takers of one bread, likewiſe as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of one body ar not in ſtrife one againſt another but in a charitable vniti ſerui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g one a nother i. Cor. xii. So may there no ſtrife nor debate be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of god. i. Cor. i. So that ani man ſhuld only care &amp; take thought for him ſelf, &amp; not care nor loke vpon his bro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers lacke, but the one muſt helpe &amp; care for the other in al things neceſſary wher he can or may. Gal. vi And no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt ſeke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, that is his, but euery one the other welth. Phi. ii. And likewiſe as of the grains of corn, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be baken bread, but through fyre, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo can not the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregacion be a right ſpiritual lofe
<pb facs="tcp:13656:11"/> wherof Paul ſpeaketh but through burning loue and charity, &amp; ſo ought the chriſtian co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregacion to be one lofe. i. Co. x. for likewiſe as many graines are ſowen to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> intent that bread ſhuld be baked of it, ſo ſoweth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great father of houſhold his precious wheate into the aker or grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of this world, to the ente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that they al ſhuld become one lofe, &amp; breake the ſupper of the lord rightly after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> words of Paul: We many are al one bread &amp; one bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dye in as muche as we are partakers of one bread i. Cor. x. And wher ſo euer the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacion is not ſo apointed, and the bread bro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken in this maner, there is the breade eaten, and the wine dronken to their dampnacion from the which god the merciful father wyl defend &amp; kepe al dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t louers of the euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinge truth through his vnexpreſſable good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes &amp; mercy. Thus haue I breifly expreſſed and ſet forth mi faith and beleue, in god the father, and god the ſon, &amp; god the holy ghoſt iii, diſtinct perſons &amp; one in the godhead &amp; co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>equall in ſubſtance, &amp; alſo my fayth &amp; beleue agreing with the true word of god, of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>craments or rather ſignificacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of baptiſm and the holy ſupper of our Lorde.</p>
            <p>Furthermore as touching the burying of my bodi, which is nothing but a peice of vile fleſh, do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, earth, duſt aſhes, it auaileth me not wher it be buried, for aſmuch as I knowe, &amp; do faithfully beleue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaying
<pb facs="tcp:13656:12"/> of ſaint Paul. i. Teſſ iiii. when the Lord him ſelf ſhal come doun fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, with a ſhoute and voyce of the archau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gel with the trumpe of god. And thoſe that ſlepe in Ieſus Chriſt, ſhal ariſe firſt before thoſe which remain the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon the earth, &amp; ſhalbe caught vp alſo with them in the cloudes, to mete the Lord in the ayr, &amp; ſo ſhal we euer be with the Lord, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore I am co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forted and ſatiſfied with theſe words. And therfore I remit &amp; referre the bu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rying of my body, vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſcreſſion of Iane my wife who is a chriſtian woman, and who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I only make my executrix.</p>
            <p>And as touching the diſtribucion of my te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peral goodes, which are but ſmal, although they are more a thouſand times then I was worthy of, for that I receiued the ſame at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hands of god, honour praiſe &amp; thankes be to him for it, and hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded me, as a faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful &amp; wiſe ſteward, to beſtow the ſame accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding to his wil. I haue partly in my life time (albeit I might haue done much more) dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed the ſame: And that, that is remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning at this preſent, aſwel moueable as vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>moueable, I gyue them aſwell heare in Ire<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>land as England holy vnto Iane my wyfe. And alſo I geue vnto her my leace of the per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſonage Tymolynge begge, my leaſe of my houſe that I nowe dwel in, my leaſe of the perſonage of Wyckelowe, my Cuſtodia of much Cabragh and Pylletteſton of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which
<pb facs="tcp:13656:12"/> I truſt the lord deputy of Ireland that ſhal be next and the counſel of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame wil grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto her, a further leace for .xxi. yeares. Alſo I geue &amp; bequeath vnto her al ſuch debtes, &amp; other ſommes of monye as are due vnto me, aſwell at the kynges maieſties handes or at anye other perſonnes. Alſo I geue vnto her ſuche ſomes of mony or lande as ſhal pleaſe the kinges maieſtie to giue me for my recom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pence of my ſeruyce doone heare to paye my debtes withal. In witneſſe of al the premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes I the ſayed Richarde Braſier haue ſubſcrybed thys my laſte wyl the daye and yeare aboue wrytten. Thys my Teſtamente is of George my ſeruauntes hande and myne.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Per me.</hi> Richarde Braſier.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London by Ihon Day: dwelling ouer Alderſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate beneth S. Martins.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
